OK, let's get started.
We have a lot of sparsity in the room.
You can see that there.
You can encode every bit over here with ones and zeros.
And there are a lot of zeros today.
It's good to compress them.
Probably, you know, you don't want these zeros.
OK, aside from jokes, today we're going to start with the memory part.
You've seen the memory part.
We've built memories.
Actually, we're going to pick up on that and build even bigger memories and build essentially a
memory hierarchy in the, in the next few lectures.
Hopefully I'll, we'll, we'll start today with the memory hierarchy also.
But I'd like to give a bit broader overview of how memory is important in systems today, because we
did a lot of things so far.
I'm going to mention that.
And that was mainly computation.
Now we're going to switch gears to something even more important and needs to be thought or
rethought even more going into the future.
But before I switch, we have this premiere of the GPU Programming lecture for those who wants to
learn about GPU programming.
It's going to happen today.
This is essentially the same lecture that was delivered some number of years ago, but if you're
interested, you can take a look at it.
And if you want to learn more about this, you can take or watch the Heterogeneous Systems course
that we have offered some number of years ago.
OK, these are the readings for today and the next lectures, You can take a look at them.
We have written this book on memory systems, which is actually, it's, it's not a book, it's a, it's
a book chapter on memory systems that introduces memory systems to hopefully a very broad audience.
So that should be a good reading for you to do.
But your books have maybe not enough material on memory systems, I would say.
So we'll cover a lot of things in the lectures that are not in the books as much, not in a nice way.
But before we jump into that, we're done with a lot of execution models.
So you know, a lot of things today on how modern computers are built and all of these principles and
also some of the implementations that we discussed are used in real systems.
I can actually say that all of these are used in real systems.
We didn't cover decoupled access execute in the lectures, but there's an optional lecture over there
you can take a look at.
That's the idea of basically decoupling computation and memory pipelines separately such that they
can proceed mostly independently of each other.
You can think of out of order processors.
What they do is they actually do out of order scheduling of instructions here in decoupled access
execute, you have an you have an instruction stream for computation and you have another
instruction stream for memory access.
And they're decoupled from each other.
And then they they basically when, when computation becomes a bottleneck, memory access can
continue.
When memory access become a bottleneck, computation can continue.
That's the idea over there.
It's an idea that's used in existing systems also.
That sort of decoupling happens a lot.
OK.
So I introduced that idea also, as you can see, OK.
And we've also covered these are actually approaches to instruction level concurrency.
It's a bit broader than the prior, prior slide.
We covered a lot of approaches starting from pipelining all the way to SIMD processing and GPUs.
Now you're familiar with many of these processing paradigms and it's good to keep thinking about the
trade-offs.
I kind of discussed that yesterday, like systolic arrays versus GPUs versus Fpgas, right?
Systolic arrays are very specialised.
As a result, their hardware cost is low, but their programmability is also low.
Their flexibility is also low.
So if you want to make it flexible, it becomes at an extra cost.
GPUs, as we discussed yesterday, they're SIMD engines and they're relatively general purpose
compared to systolic arrays, but their efficiency is low compared to systolic arrays even in matrix
computations.
But then programmability is higher.
So there is one example and there are many, many other examples that you can think of in terms of
trade-offs in these paradigms.
And this is exciting because when someone wants to build a new system, for example, assuming you are
going to do it based on existing paradigms, it's important to know the trade-offs that you're
dealing with, right?
OK.
And we've covered a lot of things across the stack.
Actually, we even looked at how to map algorithms like systolic computation, for example, to a
particular hardware.
OK.
And also good to think about what determines the widespread success of a paradigm, right?
It's, it's probably not easy to predict this because when GPUs were around the 1980s, nineteen 90s,
early 2000s, nobody has probably thought about AI as a workload that would execute on GPUs, people
who are thinking about graphics, right?
And that was a limited domain games, etcetera.
But over time, workloads change, technology changes, and you can see that some ideas may become
better than others, but this also requires you to have good programming models, good ability to
actually exploit the hardware in a good way.
OK, now let's take a.
Step back because all of the things that we discussed are important.
They're all implemented in real systems.
But a computing system is not just about processing, right?
It's also about data storage and memory.
And you've seen this picture before.
We have computation, communication, storage and memory.
We're going to look at the other parts right now today.
And you also seen this picture also.
We talked about processing a lot and we've covered a lot of processing paradigms.
Now we'll look at memory, memory and IO communication.
It's they're actually similar because in the end, memory is all about storing and communicating data
and IO and interconnects are needed to communicate the data.
And as we will see soon, memory itself is not just about storing data, but also communicating
internally.
There are a lot of interconnects, a lot of wires inside the memory.
You've seen this actually in the basic memories that we have built with flip flops, for example.
So let me give you a broad overview of why memory is so important.
I think you've seen some parts of it, but essentially it's most of our system today.
This is a picture from 20 years ago.
Right now AM DS Barcelona system.
You can see that at that time.
These are some of the earlier multi core systems.
Cores are big relatively, but still most of the system is dedicated to memory.
You can see a lot of caches inside the cores.
There are one caches, there's a memory interface, there's memory.
So most of the system is memory.
And if you look at this system, a large fraction is really memory SRAM.
We don't even see the DRAM over here if you look at it.
And then there's a communication interface.
So a good fraction of the chip is not really dedicated to computation.
You've seen GPUs, for example, GPUs, A large fraction is register files, caches, communication with
the outside world.
That's true for the cores over here also.
That's true for the neural engines over here also.
And then there's an outside communication with the memory channels.
And we're going to talk about a lot about the main memory system.
And this is if you think about memory extended their storage, right?
And that's actually a lot of transistors in the system.
And this has always been the case.
Actually, this is Intel Pentium Pro.
You've seen this picture before.
Because integration capability was lower in the past, processors did not tell even caches on the
chip.
This is the 11th level 2 cache.
And over time, we, we, we were able to put a lot more transistors and processors started eating
essentially everything else, all of the other chips that we have around.
And today you have a lot of caches on the processor chip.
It's, it's good to think about and ask the question, is this the right thing to do?
Of course, right.
Maybe we should be putting the processor on the memory chips, right.
And we're going to talk about that later on.
But that's how things have evolved because the way we design our systems, including the von Neumann
model, is very processor centric, right?
It's all about sequential execution a program executes.
It's not really about data, right?
If you think about data flow, it's a lot more about data, OK, anyway, And then this L2 cache got
consumed by the processor chip.
And you can see that this Pentium for L2 cache, the big, big part of the chip, this is more recent
processor, AMD Ryzen 2020.
You can see that LL3 cache is almost the whole chip, right?
There's also L2 cache over here.
There are L1 caches.
I didn't even include it in the green part over here.
But if you look at the, if you look at this chip, the cores, the processing parts are actually very
small fraction, right.
The rest is over here.
Global memory interconnect system management unit is the outside interfaces to communicate with the
chip.
OK and people are actually adding 3D stacking.
We're going to talk about that a little bit more today, but today it's there's exciting
technologies.
You don't grow only in the two-dimensional side, planar side.
You can actually put things on top of each other, different chips.
In this particular case, on top of the processor chip, they can put an SRAM chip that's actually
essentially used as a cache.
OK, we're going to talk about caches.
Of course, this is just to give you examples, and this is not just AMD, Intel, the general purpose
market, it's also IBM.
For example, it's a chip from IBM Power 10 from 2020.
You can see that memory is a very large fraction again over here.
And if you look around the chip, you can see that there's a lot of outside communication, PCIe
interfaces, Power, Exxon interface, memory buses, memory signalling interfaces.
So most of the chip is really about data storage and communication.
It's really about the outside world.
If you think about an outside world is actually a lot of it is memory and storage.
GPUs are a little bit better, not necessarily that much better because they can get away with let's
say smaller caches because they're not a general purpose, etcetera.
But if you look at the cords itself, there is a lot of register files inside there also.
So a good fraction of GPUs are also memory as you have seen yesterday, right?
Even inside the cords there are huge register files and the caches are still large and I could keep
going but I'll become boring I guess.
But this chip is actually.
This wafer scale chip is also a lot of memory and this is fascinating that we can actually put so
much SRAM on a wafer, right.
It's 40 gigabytes, very small actually if you think about it, it's nothing compared to existing KV
caches that we have in LLMS for example, or models.
So it's very small, but it's that's the downside of the SRAM technology as we will see.
SRAM occupies a lot of area.
So you can put very little of it on a huge wafer like this.
If it was DRAM, you could actually put a whole lot more like orders and orders of magnitude more
DRAM as we will see.
OK, So basically my point is memory is most of the platform today.
This is my picture from 2009.
I think I drew this picture for a proposal that I owed from for NSF.
We were working on scalable quality of service aware memory systems at the time.
And our point was basically you have a bunch of cores, which are the red parts over here or
accelerators, and they're all competing to access main memory, right?
And most of the chip is really cache's main memory.
And we'll see a lot of these components starting today, actually, especially today we'll talk about
different technologies, SRAM to build caches, DRAM to build main memory, and the interfaces how to
access data, for example.
But it's good to know that most of the system, what we're going to talk about today is really most
of the system what we talked all the way until lecture 19.
Well, lecture 20, I guess 20 is yesterday.
Computation is a very small fraction.
And one of the reasons is we have been very good at optimising computation, right?
And we may not be as good as optimising memory, even though we have optimised it a lot, maybe we
have not optimised it enough because you will see that the system is still by like by memory.
So if you actually think about this picture and take a blank slate, you don't know anything like the
10 year old kid example.
You know, a 10 year old kid who is smart, who can think, and who doesn't have any vested interest in
trillions of dollars or anything.
You're thrown with this picture and somebody tells you that they're dedicating almost all of their
resources, more than 99% of the hardware real estate of a single node to a memory.
And they ask you, this is, is this my bottleneck or should this be my bottleneck as a 10 year old
kid?
Probably you would say this shouldn't be your bottleneck, right?
You're putting all of your resources on it, yet it's still our bottleneck.
So it's good to think about that, right?
So going forward, we should be 10 year old kids, I think because we are actually wasting a lot of
things as you will see.
So basically we've seen actually memory many times in this course, right?
We constructed some very simple memories and we talked about memory loads, for example, and even in
pipelining when we assumed one cycle memory, the load to use delay, there's a load, there's,
there's a bubble that we had, right, because of how we construct the pipeline.
Even when you assume one cycle memory, you get a delay because of memory.
That sounds bad, right?
And we talked about load store handling, which is a very complicated part in out of order execution.
Out of order execution actually is there to tolerate a lot of the memory latencies.
We talked about stalls due to VLIW in VLIW due to long latency operations.
So memory is bottlenecking essentially everything.
Yesterday and the previous week we talked about memory banks needed in SIMD processors.
We're going to build on that more and we saw how important adding more ports or adding more banks is
to improve performance of a highly parallel computation engine.
We talked about GPU register files, we talked about systolic arrays and we talked about fine grade
multi threading to tolerate latency.
So a lot of what we did actually in this course is to tolerate latency, and a lot of that latency is
really coming from memory in the end, but we're still not very good at tolerating that latency.
OK, So this is something that I showed earlier, but this is becoming worse with workloads that are
becoming much more data intensive, like MLAI Genomics.
There's a lot of workloads.
Basically.
I'll show you some pictures over here and you will see some examples also.
And this data is increasing today and this data is enabled actually the machine learning revolution,
I guess third machine learning revolution, I don't know, I cannot keep track of it.
Maybe it'll go down again and then go up again, who knows?
But but basically the availability of data and the ability of humans to process it very fast and
efficiently has enabled the these machine learning models that we're dealing with.
But there will be more and more.
So this is an example from machine learning.
The, the large models have been requiring a lot more computation capability in very small number of
years as you can see, but also a lot more memory capability as well at the same time.
So a computation is not enough.
You really need to deal with memory.
OK, let me give you a couple of perspectives.
So from the application side, it's not just machine learning.
There are many, many applications that are actually interesting.
These are just to make you think, I'm not going to go into.
To the details of any of these, but there are a lot of papers that have been written on different
workloads and how memory is a big bottleneck in terms of its latency, in terms of bandwidth, in
terms of capacity.
And different applications are bottlenecked by different parts.
Different parts of an application are bottlenecked by different things in memory.
Sometimes it's bottleneck by the latency to access memory, sometimes it's bottleneck by capacity.
We're going to talk about capacity a lot actually in the last lecture when we talk about virtual
memory, for example.
So memory is a big bottleneck in terms of performance.
This is based on a study that we did.
I'm going to very briefly mention that later on.
We studied these workloads at Google from 2016 to 2018 and we published a paper about that.
I'll mention that paper later on.
So these were relatively early inference engines at Google and then web browsing and video playback
and capture.
And these workloads are actually very much problematic by memory in the end.
And we do a lot of work on genomics.
So I, I can tell you that genomics is also very much bottlenecked by memory.
But I'll let that go for a different.
So if you take courses from us in the future, for example, we talk a lot about genomics workloads
that are very much bottlenecked by memory.
So in the end, a lot of things that we care about scientific discovery, medical and health
applications are also bottlenecked by memory.
OK, let me give you some real data.
So performance perspective, this actually data from someone else, not my data, but this is actually
a very valid data.
**** Seitz was a chief architect of the ELF architecture.
ELF architecture was, you've seen that in out of order execution briefly.
It's essentially the competitor of Intel in 1980s, nineteen 90s.
They were building these fast out of order execution engines and after they designed a flagship
processor with **** Seitz wrote this paper and this is a famous paper because of what it says over
there.
It's the memory stupid.
It's playing with at the time there were elections in the US and somebody was running with it's the
economy stupid.
You can guess who that may be at the time.
Basically this is about it's, it's all about the memory stupid.
And basically he says with someone else in this work that they actually designed probably the
fastest processor of it's time.
It's finishing.
It's capable of finishing four instructions every cycle.
It's a super scaler processor.
Unfortunately, on these intensive memory intensive workloads, it's finishing one instruction every
five cycles or so, 5 to 7 cycles or whatever it is.
Yeah.
So basically it's operating at 120th of its peak capable peak throughput.
And the reason is basically memory.
It's waiting for memory, right?
We were talking about 1990s right now, right?
And he finishes this one page article saying that I expect that over the coming decade, memory
subsystem design will be the only important design issue for microprocessors.
And I kind of agree with them actually, because it is the only important design issue.
Everything we do is like design around that bottleneck.
OK.
This is a data that I gathered during my PhD thesis.
We did a lot of work with Intel and we, we were looking at the design of their top match like
leading edge processors at the time and the workloads that they were using to design those
processors.
And we did a lot of analysis to understand where the bottlenecks are.
And this is data summarised across like 150 workloads, important workloads.
And we see that the processor is waiting for more than 50% of the time for L2 misses, L2 cache
misses to come back from memory.
The process is basically idle, doing nothing.
OK, that's our paper and we wrote a lot of papers on this topic.
You may see that later in prefetching lectures.
OK, this is Fast forward 10 more years.
We're talking about 10-10 years intervals.
This is data from Google.
It's a beautiful paper that they published in ISCA in 2015.
According to them, this is all of their data centre workloads executing at on the cutting edge
processors that they have in their data centres.
And where, where does the time go basically during the execution of these workloads?
So back end bound is mostly waiting for memory.
That's this part over here.
There's more analysis in the paper to justify that front end bound is waiting for memory or branch
prediction.
So memory is also there.
As you can see, retiring is, you know what retires by now, it's finishing instructions, right?
It's doing what it's supposed to do.
So the way you can think of this as the processor, the cutting edge processor is doing what it's
supposed to do only 10 to 20% of the time finishing instructions.
The rest of the time it's waiting for data to come back again.
Be that 10 year old kit.
Throw this picture at the 10 year old kit.
Ask them.
I designed this thing from a performance perspective.
The sole goal of this thing is to finish instructions, and it's doing what it's supposed to be doing
10 to 10% of the time, that thing.
Old kid would say go to do something else because he probably didn't design this well or design
something else maybe do something else also design something else at least so it's good to I think
think about this right.
This is happening because of the way we're designing our systems processing is very much done in the
processor and memory is there to serve the processor.
So we'll see, I can actually keep going and going with these numbers, but it's, it's, it's really
important for you to see these numbers because if you, for example, if you go to a computer
architecture course and these, I'd actually took some of these computer architecture courses myself
also.
It may be very good, very interesting, but sometimes people miss the big perspective, right?
The perspective is, yes, you do all of that computation.
Computation is great, no question.
And we could keep optimising it forever.
The problem is somewhere else though, and that's what I'd like to instill over here.
And the reason that problem is somewhere else is because I think education doesn't understand and
show that the problem is somewhere else.
So that's why I would like to show that the problem is somewhere else.
You could actually keep doing a lot of computation, but in the end you'll be bottlenecked by memory
and everybody figures it out, as you can see, for 30 years or so.
Actually, it's more than that.
OK, anyway, this is more analysis than Google's paper, so let's talk about energy.
Energy is actually a lot more important today, and energy is much worse.
So hardware cost was bad, performance is bad.
If you think about energy of memory access, that's much worse.
In the end, and I'll give you some data.
This is data from NVIDIA in 2015, Bill Daly and media's chief scientist.
You can argue with the numbers, The numbers have changed because things have scaled in the last 11
years, but the relative differences did not change as much.
So what is depicted here is the cost in terms of energy of a computation operation.
It's a 64 bit double precision floating point operation.
It's a very hefty operation and the rest is basically communication.
So communicating some, for example, accessing 8 kilobytes of SRAM at the 256 bit granularity is 50
picojoules, for example, it's already larger than that.
As you can see, accessing DRAM is 16 nanojoules.
So if you do the calculation, that's 800X more than that 20 picojoules.
OK, it's good to think about that.
And also accessing from here to here in the chip is 1 nanojoules.
That's also a lot, right?
It's a big chip, of course, 20 millimetres by 20 millimetres.
So you can see that the communication is really the bottleneck in terms of energy because the
interconnects actually take a lot of energy.
And there's also a historical perspective to this, because we were able to scale technology really
well using Moore's Law and then ART scaling.
Transistors became smaller and smaller and smaller.
They became much more energy efficient.
As a result, the computation became much more energy efficient.
Unfortunately, interconnects did not scale very well because in the in the end, interconnects are
basically how far you communicate data on and it's very hard to scale them unless you go to some
other technology where you reduce the length of the interconnects, which we're also going to talk
about.
And going off chip is actually much worse because you actually need to drive huge interconnects that
go somewhere else.
And for that drive, you need to actually have a lot of power and you go out and then to to get to
some other chip like dear, I mean to drive more.
That's the reason you get actually this 800 X difference, OK, 800X.
People try to optimise that a lot today.
That number is the distinction, the difference between a memory access and a high precision
arithmetic operation, maybe 160 X.
Going below 150 is very, very, very, very difficult.
In the end, if you can do it, then you can actually design something much more energy efficient.
But people were not able to go beyond that as much.
So it's good to think about.
Does it really make sense to move data, right?
Why don't I actually do operations without moving the data?
OK, that was expensive arithmetic operation.
Let's look, we get a simpler arithmetic operation.
This is from another paper, again from NVIDIA.
And this shows that this is the energy cost of a 32 bit integer operation, which is simpler.
And this is DM access, energy cost of DM.
So the relative disparity increases.
As you can see if you make computation cheaper and smaller, memory access becomes more costly
relatively.
So that's 6400 X.
We're not even talking about storage yet.
We're talking about accessing the DRAM.
If you go to storage like SSD, multiply that by another 10X at least.
So the numbers go crazy, right?
So if you bring back the 10 year old kid out and say give them.
Give them these numbers, they'll say, are you crazy?
Are you moving data?
It doesn't make sense to move data, basically, right?
That's the key in the end.
This is actually true for even larger scale interconnects, like when you go to Internet.
Moving data is actually costly.
And we're moving a lot of data across the Internet as well.
But even with our basic systems, even within a system, we're moving data a lot.
OK.
So you can actually look at these numbers and look at the costs.
So we did a lot of studies to understand the effects of this data movement and also the way we're
designing our systems on essentially all metrics we care about energy, performance, hardware, real
estate, etcetera.
This is the study that I mentioned with Google that we did between 2016 and 2018.
We analysed those workloads that I showed you including tensor flow of inference, Chrome browsing
and video encoding and decoding.
And we found out that on average use cases in mobile workloads, more than 60% of the total system
energy is spent on moving data across the hierarchy.
This is not even this.
These are workloads that are resident in memory.
You don't even go to storage.
And these if you go to storage, this number increases.
Yes, yeah.
So that's a very good question.
That's a different question.
Not necessarily, because heat depends on the intensity of how fast you can actually heat up.
Something like how fast you can spend the energy, basically.
So in general, the heat is usually produced by computation units that are really operating at high
frequency.
But communication also effects heat.
But if you were only doing communication because that's slower and you're not operating at extremely
high frequency, the heat would be lower I would guess.
That's a very good question.
OK, so this is an example.
These are not the worst use cases.
These are general use cases where people use cell phones or Chromebooks, for example.
More recently, we've also worked with Google circa like 2018 to 2021.
We analysed the neural network models that they used in in their Pixel phone, for example.
These are commercial neural network models that they used.
And we found out that more than 90% of the total system energy spent on memory in these large
models.
I think I've, I've shown you a picture, a version of this picture very early on in this course, but
you can see that these are, this is before LLM times.
So the larger models are LSTMS, transducers, they're also of course convolutional neural networks,
recurrent neural networks, etcetera.
For the larger models, you can see that most of the energy is really spent on DM accesses and off
chip interconnect CPU.
Well, in this case it's an accelerator.
It's a systolic array base accelerator.
It's the HTPU that we discussed earlier.
The accelerator is not consuming a lot of power in the end.
That's true for smaller models also, but large models are much worse essentially.
There's also another thing to say here.
Clearly these models are big and you're communicating a lot, but there's another reason why.
Energy of data movements starts dominating things because if you optimise computation, if you
accelerate computation, it becomes faster, it becomes more energy efficient and the part that you
didn't optimise becomes start starts dominating, right.
So Zamdar's law in the end.
So in systems where you have a very specialised accelerator, many systems have that.
In machine learning today, computation has become less of a bottleneck and data moment and memory
have become more of a bottleneck because it's kind of been ignored in the sense that it's not been
accelerated.
OK, it's good to think about that also.
So that's one of the reasons why we do a lot of work on processing in memory.
Basically, the key idea is as opposed to moving data from memory to the processor CPU, why not
actually put processing capability inside the memory chips, right?
Then you move data very little, keep it inside the memory.
So you can take a look at some of the work that we've been doing.
We have a lot of papers and interviews, etcetera, articles, OK, So that was the performance energy
perspectives.
Now let's talk about robustness.
Robustness you've seen for example, you've seen the row hammer things.
I'm going to go through this relatively quickly, but this is also becoming worse essentially.
So memory dominates a lot of the robustness issues.
This is a study that we did with Facebook a long time ago, 2013 or so.
And essentially we found a very positive strong correlation with the density of the DRAM chip that's
employed in the server and the failure rate, the server's experience.
This is on production data centre, data centres that are employed at Facebook across all of the
world.
That's a lot of computers, actually.
This is very statistically significant data.
They don't allow us to publish how much memory we examined and how many servers we examined because
that's confidential information for them.
They don't want to reveal the size of their infrastructure.
But this is a.
A lot of data actually and very, it's also, it's a correlation based study that shows that denser
memory chips cause more problems, more errors.
Essentially you get some bit flip and that actually takes down the server, right.
OK, there's a lot more analysis of this and essentially as memory capacity increases, system
reliability reduces.
If you're interested, there's more analysis of this in this paper and also other papers.
So we actually built a lot of infrastructure.
You've seen some of this infrastructure in the past also to, to, to analyse these memory issues in
terms of both latency, energy errors, robustness.
So if you have an FPGA and with an FPGA based memory controller, if you can actually change the
access patterns to memory, change the voltage, change the latency parameters, you can discover a
lot of things about what's happening in these memory chips.
This was the infrastructure that we built at Carnegie Mellon and essentially it consists of FPGA
boards, DM modules, some temperature controller and also voltage controller, etcetera.
And we actually can test different types of DM chips including HPM chips and you can take a look at
that this the HPM testing infrastructure.
We also discover a lot of interesting things about HPM over here.
These are open source, people can take a look at it.
But essentially this is a laboratory that we have at ETETH right now where we actually have a lot of
these things, more than 120 or so.
Somebody can verify that, but maybe we would.
Is it not 150 yet?
OK, OK.
We should shoot for 500 or so.
Basically the the capacity is the, the capacity of the room is what's limiting us right now anyway.
So you've seen the row hammer phenomena.
I'm not going to go over this in detail, but essentially, as chips become denser, they become more
vulnerable to errors because the cells that we're going to study a lot more in the later part of
today, the cells become more smaller and cells become closer to each other.
As a result, the data that's stored in one cell gets affected by whatever you're doing in the
vicinity of that cell.
And RAW Hammer is very interesting because this is the first example of the fact that you can
actually predictably induce bit flips in most.
You can remove most today.
It's all DM memory chips if you know what you're doing.
So this is not supposed to be happening.
Basically, by accessing memory, you should not be able to induce errors.
So, so far, for example, we have seen a lot of computation mechanisms, right?
If you keep doing additions in a ALU, you should not get errors, right?
Same thing over here.
If you keep doing accessing memory, you should not get errors.
But we're getting these errors in memory and they're they're, they're actually pretty common these
days.
OK, I think you've seen these slides, so I'll go through this relatively quickly.
But we will see the structure of memory today.
This is an abstraction.
All memory in the end is 2 dimensional array of cells.
It's a hierarchical 2 dimensional array of cells.
To get more and more memory, there needs to be a hierarchy, as we will see.
So in the smaller version, there is a 2 dimensional array.
And if you want to access one bit, you need to activate the row that contains that bit.
Essentially we'll see the granularity, etcetera later today.
But in Row Hammer, you activate one row and activation of a row is essentially driving that
interconnect with high voltage.
You'll see this in more detail later today.
Again, essentially you open the row and then you access the data.
And then if you want to access some other row, you drive the word line to a low voltage, basically
close that row.
And if you keep doing this repeatedly, you get bit flips in adjacent rows.
That's what Row Hammer is about.
It's basically fundamentally due to the way we access memory, but it's also, there are some
underlying physical aspects that we're device level aspects that we're not going to get into.
So if you do this hammering enough times before the cells get refreshed, some cells in the victim
rows get corrupt.
They lose charge little by little with every access.
And you will see why this is happening in DM soon, because we're going to talk about DM technology.
Each DM cell has charge stored in it.
And that charge leaks every time you do some sort of hammering effect.
OK, we'll get back to this.
But clearly this should not be happening, right?
Because whenever you access some, some memory location, you should not change some other memory
location, right?
That's something that we should not.
If you, if you think about a load access, for example, we've seen Isas, right?
We're doing a load access and that's getting translated into these row accesses in DRAM.
And you keep doing this repeatedly going to the same row.
You should not be changing any data, right, architecturally.
The problem is this architecturally changes some data that belongs to potentially some other
application, right?
Or some or the operating system.
So you will see in the virtual memory lectures why this can be.
This circumvents the operating system.
OK.
But today this is a robustness problem because this problem is getting worse.
So we want to build higher capacity memories.
And if you want to build a higher capacity memory, you want to store more bits per square
millimetre, right?
In the past you had smaller memories.
Basically you want to make the cells smaller and closer to each other.
And as you do that, this sort of effects increase.
You basically start getting much more noise and interference and also you have the fundamental
capability of storing data is lower in the cell because in a smaller cell you have smaller charge,
right?
It's good to think about this.
That's why this sort of problem is increasing and it's not going to become better unless we figure
out a much better technology, which is also not easy today.
OK, so we'll, we'll get back to row Hammer in the virtual memory lecture, but you will see why this
is happening.
So this has security implications.
You've seen this before.
Also.
Basically people have devised attacks, especially Google to begin with, after reading our paper,
they devised attacks to take over a system, gain internal privileges.
And we will see how that happens in the virtual memory lecture.
And this shows that memory is critical for robustness.
This is just one example.
There are a bunch of other examples that I can give you, but we don't have time.
So it's really affecting everything that we care about.
I would say memory is really critical for computing.
So we've covered performance, energy, robustness, cost, but there are also other things, form
factor, quality of service, predictability, because when you're running multiple applications, for
example, one application is trying to access memory, but it's denied service by some other
application potentially.
This happens a lot actually in real systems and sustainability, which we don't have great metrics
for, but it's good to think about going into the future like how does the, how does the how does
memory affect sustainability?
I know for sure that a lot of the hardware that we have is memory actually.
OK, so let's now jump into the fundamentals of memory.
Hopefully I've convinced you that there is a lot to see here.
In my opinion, actually if I were starting doing, if I were starting a company, I would make it
memory centric as opposed to processor centric, right?
Because processor centric, a lot of people have done it.
It's boring and you'll be bottleneck in the end memory and it's very difficult to distinguish
yourself in terms of something new, right?
But if you start doing something memory centric, you can actually innovate a lot.
First of all, you will not be competing with people who can design processes extremely well.
And you will also potentially being much more disruptive, right?
So I think companies or research, I think company and research has some similarities because in the
in the research you're trying to do something big.
Yeah.
And you need to actually think about that.
OK, so let's go into memory fundamentals unless there are any questions.
OK.
And I'm going to start with memory organization and technology, but before I start with that, memory
looks like this for us, right?
You have loads and stores.
From the programmer's perspective, that's what you do.
You don't care how disturbs you, right?
From a programmer's perspective, this is a very high level programmer who doesn't care about
performance.
Now if you care about performance, you need to know what's inside there, right?
We talked about that in GPUs, for example.
You need to lay out your data such that different accesses go to different banks, right?
If everything goes to the same bank, you're in trouble.
OK, OK, so but I will mention this still because we're going to get to virtual memory.
What the programmer sees is virtual.
It's not real.
Basically.
That's why it's called virtual.
And the programmer can assume the memory is infinite.
The reality is physical memory size is much smaller than what the programmer assumes.
And the system itself, the system software and hardware cooperatively maps the virtual addresses to
physical memory, and that's what virtual memory is all about.
We're going to see that in direction mechanisms.
In other words, the system automatically manages the physical memory space transparently to the
programmer.
This makes programmers life a lot easier.
So we're going to introduce this more today.
We're going to talk a lot about physical memory.
We're going to ignore the virtual part.
So the upside of this virtual abstraction for the programmer is programmer doesn't need to know the
physical size of memory.
They don't need to manage it.
Also a physical memory can appear as a huge one to the programmer, a small one, and life is easier
for the programmer in the end, which is what we would like.
Like that's what we did without order execution also, right?
We didn't ask the programmer to tell us which instructions can be executed independently.
We did that for the programmer.
Under the hood, ISA is still 1 moment.
In a sense, this is also similar.
Unfortunately, now the system software and the architecture needs to be much more complex, and we
will see that complexity in the virtual memory lectures.
And this is actually a very successful classic example of the programmer microarchitecture.
Trade off.
So this requires, of course indirection and mapping between virtual to physical address spaces.
What the programmer sees virtual address space that's in the ISA.
And there's some indirection and mapping mechanisms to the physical memory that we're going to
discuss today.
OK, so we're going to talk about physical memory today.
And you need a larger level of storage to manage a small amount of physical memory automatically.
So virtual memory actually requires a larger amount of storage.
And for that physical memory has a backing store which is disk today.
Today it's s s, DS.
But then you can also have hard disks, you can also have tapes.
So the hierarchy, memory hierarchy extends actually quite large, right?
Registers SRAM caches, main memory, DRAM, s s, DS, hard disk drives, tape and who knows what else
out there, right?
So we will first start with the physical memory system and we're going to ignore this virtual to
physical indirection.
We will get back to it later, hopefully time will permit.
But before we start with the physical memory system, I think we should also think about like what is
the ideal thing that we want from the system, right?
It's always good to have this perspective.
I'm designing with a blank slate.
If I had the idea, if I could do the ideal thing, what is that ideal thing I could do?
And we've done this kind of for other things.
So I'd like to talk about this a little bit.
So we talked about pipelining, for example, right?
Ideally you want no pipeline stalls, right?
You remember that lecture?
We want perfect data flow, meaning no dependencies.
Ideally.
Again, ideally, if you have dependencies, if you need to communicate, we want zero cycle
interconnect.
That sounds good.
We want enough functional units such that we can do as much, we can exploit as much parallelism as
possible.
And ideally you want 0 latency compute.
This is what I want.
Of course, I don't get it necessarily right, but it's good to think about this from the instruction.
From the instruction supply, again, we want 0 latency access.
This is now becoming our part of memory.
Also, we want infinite capacity ideally or it just enough capacity to not go out, zero costs and
perfect control flow.
We talked about perfect control flow, branch prediction for example, right?
At least branch prediction as part of perfect control flow data supply is also a memory.
Again, we want 0 latency access, infinite capacity, infinite bandwidth and 0 cost.
I guess more summary in a in a more summarised manner.
Ideal memory is 0 latency, 0 cost, 0 energy, infinite capacity and infinite bandwidth, right?
Sounds good.
The problem is all of these conflict with each other, right?
And I will, for example, if you want to build very high capacity, latency becomes a problem.
I didn't even talk about robustness over here.
As you can see, right, if you want to build extremely high capacity, robustness becomes a problem,
Energy becomes a problem.
So they conflict with each other and we're going to see that conflict.
And that conflict will lead to a memory hierarchy.
You cannot get small.
You cannot get large to be fast.
So you have small and fast, and then you'll have large and slow, and increasingly you'll have slower
and larger memories that are far out from the processor.
Again, this is the processor centric perspective.
It's good to think about that, right?
Processor is the king, and everything else down that in that memory hierarchy is going to serve the
king.
The question is, do you want that king?
That's a very valid question these days.
OK, so let's talk about memory erase because we're going to build up this memory and every memory
will be quite similar to each other in terms of how we build it up.
You've seen part of this picture in the past, but essentially how can we store data as a question?
Like we've seen flip flops and latches a lot early on.
These are very fast, but very, very expensive.
Every bit costs 10s of transistors, static RAM, SRAM, this, we'll describe it soon.
This is relatively fast, not as fast as flip flops, but it's still expensive.
Not as fast, not as expensive as flip flops.
One bit costs about 6 transistors, maybe 8 if you want to accelerate things a little bit.
Dynamic RAM.
This is DRAM main memory row hammer exists here.
We will describe it soon.
Also this is slower reading and chart leakage destroys content.
So I need to refresh it.
That's why it's called dynamic.
You need to continuously refresh it.
It needs special process for manufacturing because it has a capacitor included.
So you cannot actually manufacture it the same way you manufacture logic.
Logic doesn't have capacitors, it has transistors.
And capacitor needs very special manufacturing conditions.
So as a result, it has to be a bit separate, and that's one of the reasons why memory and logic has
separated from each other over the course of the history.
The good news is it's very cheap, so one bit costs only one transistor plus one capacitor, so the
density.
Of this memory is very high, so you can build very high capacity memories using dynamic random
access memory and then you can think about other storage technology like flash memory.
These are SSDs today, hard disks.
How many people still use hard disks here?
OK, some people do.
How many people don't use hard disks anymore?
OK, so you're in 2026 as you can see, right?
You can see that some memories are replacing others, at least in some use cases.
And then there's tape.
Anybody uses tape here?
OK For what?
Music.
OK, I see music.
Yes, but I mean music, Sure.
But in the past, like I started with tape, for example, like when you how many people had a
Commodore 64 here, for example?
Nobody.
I had.
I had one of those.
OK, maybe you had one.
OK, your dad had one.
OK, So I had that and I used to play games, I used to program and essentially you have a tape over
there and that tape has your programs, right?
People still use magnetic tapes and data centres for cold data, for example.
This tape is actually very efficient in terms of storage.
But basically these storage technologies increasingly are much slower.
They require special manufacturing.
Clearly tape is a good example of that there.
The upside is the big upside is they're non volatile, meaning if you plug the power off, they still
keep the data.
That's not true for any of the upper technologies, flip flops, aesthetic RAM, dynamic RAM, you turn
the power off, they lose their data.
OK, so there's also other benefit to storage technology, as you can see.
And the other benefit is these are very cheap.
One transistor stores many bits and sometimes there are no transistors involved.
There's a different way of storing things and as a result you can actually make things much denser.
But the key take away if you look over here is there is a huge trade off between speed and cost.
In other words, speed and capacity, right?
Usually capacity and cost are similar to each other.
And this is exactly the reason why we will have a memory hard because we cannot build high capacity
things fast in the end.
OK, let me cover this and then we'll take a break.
So all memories look like this.
In the end, you have an array that stores cells, 2 dimensional array.
We're going to make it 3 dimensional later on potentially.
And the goal is to efficiently store large amounts of data.
You supply an address and you get data, and the granularity of the address should address
essentially everything you want in the array, with the addressability of course.
And you have some number of bits that you get.
So you have a memory array, you have some address selection logic which selects one row of the
array.
And there's some read out circulated that reads some column in the array.
And the column may be M bits over here, for example.
So an M bit value can be read or written at each unique M bit address.
All values can be accessed, but only M bits at a time.
Now we're building an interface to the array, right?
And all memories have this sort of interface.
In the end, this sort of access restriction, the fact that you cannot access everything, anything
you want immediately, enables more compact organization in the end.
Well, you've seen this array in the past, right?
This is our array.
And remember that this was a 4 * 3.
There are 4 entries and it's 3 bits.
In this case, address is 2 bits and the granularity is 3 bits, right?
It's a small array, but they can be bigger.
So basically we have a 2 dimensional array of bit cells.
Each bit cells stores one bit and you have two to the north rows and M columns.
Depth is the number of rows, width is number of columns and array size is clearly depth and width.
And you can basically, you've seen this before.
Also basically you have a mapping of the addresses to data.
This is an example.
Again I will not go through this because we've done this before.
An address specifies which row you're looking at and the width could be 3, but width also could be
like one row may have one million things and you select only eight of them, for example.
So there needs to be some other circuitry which is called a multiplexer as you know, to select 8 out
of 1,000,000, right?
Depending on the address bits.
OK, a larger and wider memory array looks like this.
Basically you increase the address and you have more words as you can see.
And then this case data is 32 bits.
So store I will I will generalize this a little bit.
This is a general way of looking at memory.
There's an address decoder, an address coming in and this is a 2 dimensional structure.
You have word lines, you have bit lines.
This is exactly the memory that we looked at four by three except storage nodes in one column are
connected to the bit line over here.
So sometimes you don't show that Max because it depends on how you sense the data.
So when you enable.
Word line, for example, let's say you supply address 10.
That's the active word line right now.
This is the activate that I showed you in the RAM with the row hammer.
Basically all of these bits in the same that are connected to the word line that are in this row get
connected to their bit lines.
And they they basically perturb their bit lines in some way depending on the technology in a way
that's very, the physics are very much dependent on the technology.
But essentially you read out the values that are stored in these storage nodes by activating the
word line.
Makes sense hopefully, right?
So if this was 1,000,000 bits wide in terms of number of columns, number of bit lines, all those
1,000,000 bits would be activated.
And if you need only eight of them, you need to have a multiplexer at the end to select which ones
you want.
So essentially content of the entire line is available, right?
OK, how is access controlled?
Essentially you have access transistors that connect the bit, store bit storage to the bit line.
These transistors are switches.
You know that from lecture one, right?
Access is controlled by the word line.
So when you enable the word line, what happens is really there's an access transistor over here, as
you can see this in DRAM, that enables this DRAM capacitor, which stores the data to be connected
to the bit line.
And there's some sensing circuitry that senses whether there's charge in the capacitor or there's no
charge in the capacitor below some noise margin, of course, above some noise margin.
So that's the sensing circuit in SRAM.
The sensing depends on the technology as well as robustness requirements, etcetera.
But SRAM is cross coupled inverters as you have seen early in the course.
You can see that there's an access transistor over here, there's another access transistor over
here.
You can read both the positive data that's stored and the complement of it.
Well, the value that's stored and the complement of it, right.
So there are two bit lines in this case.
And you can, if you have two bit lines, you can also play tricks with sensing.
You can do differential sensing by doing better comparison, better, you can get better noise
margins, etcetera.
We're not going to go into all of those in this course.
But essentially the key take away is you have some access transistor that gets enabled when you
drive high voltage on the word line, right?
And that that enables the storage node to drive the bit line in some way.
And there's some sensing circuitry that senses what data is stored in the storage node.
This is all types of memory.
Actually, all types of memory works very similarly.
Flash memory is also very similar.
There are some slight differences because of the density of and the way things are stored.
But in the end, what you're doing is activating a row and sensing the value in all of the cells that
are in that row.
OK, so building larger memories requires larger memory arrays, and you've seen that large is slow.
The key question becomes how do we make the memory large without making it too slow?
Clearly, if you have a single monolithic array, that becomes too slow.
So we want to divide the memory into smaller arrays and interconnect the arrays to input output
buses.
So a large memories, as I said earlier, are essentially hierarchical area structures.
We're going to impose hierarchy on this instead of building a single monolithic array that's like 1
billion by 1 billion.
That sounds terrible because now we have to build a huge decoder and a huge multiplexer.
We're not going to do that.
We're going to impose hierarchy, and we're going to see this hierarchy when we continue this.
OK, this is a good place to take a break.
Well, let's be back at 1520 and we'll continue with this hierarchy and we'll introduce a concept
that we actually studied, which is banking.
OK, I think we can get started now.
So now we're going to build the hierarchy of memory arrays.
And a key component of this hierarchy is memory banking.
And we've seen the idea of memory banking in SIMD processors and also yesterday when we discussed
GPU.
So the the general idea is banking or it's also called interleaving.
And the problem it's trying to solve is multiple.
One is if you have a single monotic large memory array, this takes too long to access.
It also doesn't allow you to enable multiple access in parallel, at least cheaply unless you have
many ports to memory.
So it can solve both of these problems, meaning you can reduce the latency of memory array access
and also enable multiple access in parallel by dividing that large monolithic array into multiple
banks that can be accessed independently either in the same cycle or consecutive cycles.
And you've seen this right with.
I'm going to show you the same picture again in this.
Basically each bank is smaller than the entire memory storage.
The various memory is essentially partitioned into multiple smaller arrays, Let's say 8 banks.
Today you have 16 banks easily within a single DM chip.
Each bank is smaller than the entire memory.
Storage and access to different banks can be overlapped.
Of course, the key issue becomes how do you map data to different banks?
In other words, how do you interleave data across banks?
That's why this is called so-called interleaving.
You're really interleaving the data across different banks, different physical structures that
comprise a larger memory.
So we have seen this, this is from the SIMD architectures lecture.
And also yesterday I I discussed this and this is one way of designing A-16 bank memory.
For example, every cycle you can start an access to a different bank and every cycle you can get
data from a different bank.
That's the idea.
Another way of designing it would be having many address and data buses such that you can start the
access concurrently to all of those banks and get data concurrently out of all of those banks.
The difficulty over there is of course you have a lot of address and data buses, right, because you
need to send the address to all of the banks concurrently.
And that may not be easy to do if this is not an on chip memory.
If the memory is off chip, meaning you're accessing Adm chip that's outside the processor for
example, then the number of address and data buses, the number of wires you have is really going
outside the chip, right.
And this really determines how big your chip is, how costly your chip is.
So having a single address and databus per bank is very expensive, whereas having a single address
and databus for all the banks that is shared consecutively in use consecutive in consecutive cycles
to access different banks is much cheaper.
So we will see that essentially all DM chips today have a single address and databus that that is
shared across all of the banks, right?
Because they don't want a lot of pins because pins are costly and we will see this soon.
So this is a generalised memory structure and especially like main memory structure, you can see DM
over here.
Let's build it up.
So you have two-dimensional array of cells.
This is going to be called the bank columns and rows and a particular set of cells inside a row.
A set of columns essentially can be your cache block as we will see later on.
And you can see ADRM chip consists of multiple banks and we put many DRM chips together to form a
rank to essentially a wider interface and also higher capacity.
Here all DRM chips are packaged together so that they can respond to the same command.
For example.
We will discuss this in a little bit and then you can have this call the DRM module or rank.
There could be multiple ranks per module also, but you can have actually multiple DRM ranks or
multiple DRM modules connected to a memory channel which is controlled by a memory controller.
And you can have many memory channels.
So this is going to be the type of hierarchy that you can.
You can see that this is some N dimensional, right?
This is 1 dimension, another one, another one, another one.
So it's an N dimensional hierarchy.
There's another example over here which is essentially showing the same thing in a different way,
and you can certainly read papers related to it in DM.
People also separate the channel into a command bus, address bus and databus.
So memory controller sends a command.
It can also send data if it's a right command, for example, and that command determines what the DM
chip should do.
And then there's.
An address, but that could accompany the commands like read from this address, right?
That could be one of the commands that you sent.
You're going to see that this is actually even more finer granularity soon.
OK, so we're going to see the structure a little bit more.
But I should also say that in the cutting edge, these memories are not necessarily planar.
So if you look at this, this looks kind of planar, right?
But people are building memories on top of each other also.
So you have a memory die on top of that memory die.
You have another memory die, another memory die, another memory die, another memory die.
And you can also have logic, logic die under the memory die.
And you can put all of these together and they can get connected to each other through some
interconnect.
And that interconnect technology becomes crucial like how how many of these interconnects, how many
of these wires you can put to communicate across these different layers or different dies?
And how thin are those layers, how robust are those layers?
They all determine how much memory bandwidth you can supply to the logic layer underneath.
So this is something that's quite exciting in development.
High bandwidth memory, for example, looks like this.
And that's essentially what's used in GPUs today, at least the high end GPUs, also high end systolic
arrays like TP us, they use actually high bandwidth memory.
And the reason is the memory bandwidth requirements of these accelerators is huge, right?
And the and the reason you get higher memory bandwidth over here compared to a planer thing that
looks like this is here you're limited by the pins in terms of how much data you can put out of the
chip or get into the chip, right?
The pins are big, so you need to actually move the data through those huge things and you are
limited by the space planar space of the ship.
This is also called shoreline of the ship.
If you think about the ship as an island, there's a shoreline in the ship and you have very limited
area and also a limited power in terms of how many pins you can add.
And this 3 dimensional architecture overcomes some of this, assuming that you can build these
interconnects much smaller because here you don't have those pins, you're connecting things through
some different interconnect technology.
It's called through silicon MIAs or hybrid bonding or some multi technology.
So going forward, this is going to change a lot.
It's already changing a lot in the space of computing and memory.
You can see that high performance chips are all using this.
And the reason is you can get a very high bandwidth access, like thousands of these interconnects
can be communicating data to some logic underneath, right?
Of course, one of the issues when you have this sort of 3D stacking is where does the heat go,
right?
So heats and heats and thermals become more difficult.
So this is from a paper that we wrote about some time ago to improve memory bandwidth in this 3D
stacked memories.
But this is one way of using 3D stacked DM.
You can have a processor, let's say a GPU, underneath many DM layers, or you can have stacked memory
and connected to a processor through some silicon interposer through some other substrate.
Basically this is essentially how things are designed today.
It's called 2 1/2 D Also, the memory is itself 3 dimensional.
As you can see 3 dimensional dies, they're connected to each other.
You have very high bandwidth.
The processor to avoid some of the heat and thermal issues is separated from the memory, but there's
still high bandwidth communication that happens through the silicon interposer.
Not as high bandwidth as what this would provide, but still not bad.
Let's say this is what a GPU kind of looks like today.
You have a GPU and you have a bunch of DM, high bandwidth memory DM next to it.
OK, so this is just to give you that there are other technologies that are coming up, but I'm going
to show you examples from planar technology to begin with.
But these other technologies are quite interesting.
For example, you can actually, you can actually fabricate the logic layer separately from the memory
layer and you can use a very good logic process for the logic layer.
That's not done yet, but it's going to be done going forward.
I believe with HPM 4, HPM 5, HPM 6, etcetera.
You can have a very strong logic layer, just like a very nice cutting it chip, and you can actually
have very nice memory layers also that's customized for fabrication of memory DRAM and you can
connect them together.
And this is now becoming processing near memory, right?
You have processing right next to memory, and you can customise that logic there to be an
accelerator, for example.
OK, so let me give you the top down view of the DM system.
And then we're going to see the bottom up view, and then we're going to see more of that.
So this is a hierarchical structure.
As I said, in the top part you have a channel and then you connect to a module.
It's also called DIM rank and then rank and then chip and then bank and then rowing column, right?
And then there's a cell over here.
Each rowing column intersections a cell.
So this is what?
System looks like right, you have the processor and you have a bunch of memory channels.
In this particular case you have two, there are some number of bits, 64 bits let's say.
So that's actually 64 pins coming out of the processor and each channel has multiple Dimms as you
can see dual in line memory modules and each dim has some chips over here, but we will see.
So a DIM looks like this, it's essentially A module and there are chips attached to both sides
potentially.
And the reason we have dim is such that we can get more capacity, right?
So each chip is small capacity.
If you put eight of these chips together, you get 8X more capacity.
If you also use the backside of the DIM in this planar structure, you get 16X more capacity.
So it's good from a capacity perspective, right?
So this is each side is also called a rank.
So a rank is a collection of eight chips, in this particular case, rank zero and rank one, right?
So your data can be in either in rank 0 or rank one.
Now rank is interesting because ranks have share an address and command bus and there's a chip
select over here.
They also share the data bus, as you can see.
So you can parallelise accesses to the ranks you can start access to in parallel.
But you can only read from one bank in a given cycle, right?
You can see the MUX over here and you can read 64 bits.
OK, so that is the increased granularity we'll build it will, will, will go down in the granularity
soon.
Yes, yeah, yeah.
So this is serial presence detect.
This basically is a small non volatile memory structure that the memory controller can communicate
with and identify what kind of chip it's dealing with.
So it's some bookkeeping information for example, you can do more things over there, but the main
reason is to enable the memory controller to talk to the memory dim and understand what what
timings to use for example.
Makes us very good question.
It's usually there needs to be some sort of non volatile memory to enable that sort of
communication.
OK, so you can see that each rank is independent except for the data and address and command buses.
And whenever you're accessing rank zero, chip select is set to 0 and rank one chip select is set to
1.
So there are two chip select signals that decide which one is enabled.
And so you can see that even though you may start accesses in parallel in different ranks, there's a
rank switching penalty.
Actually, when you actually want to switch from rank zero to rank 1, you have some time, some time
needs to pass.
This is a timing parameter.
There are a lot of timing parameters to access DRAM and main memory and also flash, OK?
But that's the idea.
This enables you both a higher parallelism and also higher capacity, as you can see.
So that's the purpose of hierarchy as we discussed, right?
OK.
If you break down a rank, each rank consists of, in this particular case, 8 chips.
And remember from a rank, we are getting 64 bits here.
Each chip supplies an 8 bit portion of those 64 bits.
OK.
The reason we have this is this way we can make the chip less costly because now the chip needs to
supply only 8 bits as opposed to 64 bits, meaning each chip doesn't need to have as many pins.
Less pin out, less cost.
But we can also still get a wide interface by putting multiple chips together.
So it's called a rank because this is like a rank of soldiers.
How many of you have been to the military?
OK, so you probably know what a rank of soldiers is, right?
You are, you form a rank and then the commander says do this, raise your hand and he raise your
hand, right?
Everybody does the same thing.
Each ship responds to that.
Maybe, maybe not everybody does the same thing.
OK, the in this case, everybody does the same thing.
It's better than soldiers in this case because it's not, let's say, prone to the human deficiencies,
these chips, they are prone to other deficiencies, but not the human ones.
But essentially these are these, they respond to the same command there you receive the same address
and they give the different data.
Essentially, that's the idea over here.
And the reason we have it is because we want to keep the chips less costly with a smaller interface,
fewer pins, and we still want to get a higher interface, a larger interface, OK, OK.
And then inside the chip you have some number of banks, in this particular case 8.
And you know this is the same banks that we have seen actually earlier.
Each chip consists of these banks and each bank is independent, except they share the data bus
outside over here, as we have seen.
So you can start and access in each bank or they also share the address and commandness.
It's not, which is not shown here.
You can start and access every cycle from a different bank and it can get data every cycle from a
different bank.
That's the idea.
It's the same bank that we have seen pictured in a different way over here.
This way the chip interface is still 8 bits and each bank can supply 8 bits in a given cycle.
But you have a lot more parallelism and also you have a higher capacity.
OK, now each bank is the 2 dimensional array that we started with rows and columns.
In this particular case there may be 32,000 rows and I guess 32,000 columns.
In this case 2 kilobytes.
No, that's 16,016 thousand columns.
So normally people try to make the array size like square, but columns may be may need to be larger
because you may need some sensor fires as we will see at the row buffer.
So essentially you get 8 bits out of the structure and the activation.
Essentially you need to activate if you want to access, for example this column over here, there's
some access granularity which is 8 bits over here.
As you can see, you activate that row because with the row address that's coming from the memory
controller.
And then you this row gets placed into the row buffer, it gets sensed the entire row, 2 kilobytes of
row.
And then you get the column address again also from the memory controller.
And you, you Multiplex out the chip multiplexes out the right 8 bits based on that column address
from the row that's sensed.
OK.
So you activate the entire row 2 kilobytes to get 8 bits out of it.
OK, so let's dig deeper to the DM bank operation.
I'll, I'll also introduce some commands over here as to how we access things.
So we have these two-dimensional array columns and rows.
This, this view of a bank is also an abstraction.
Actually internally, I'm not going to break this abstraction right now.
A little bit later I will.
Internally, a bank consists of many cells and other structures that enable access to cells like
transition capacitors.
And we're going to see some of that later, But at an abstract level, there's a row buffer.
This is equivalent to the size of a row and it's essentially sensing structure sends amplifiers.
It's really like an SRAM structure.
Each, each thing over here is a cross coupled inverter.
Initially this is empty.
And if the memory controller says I want to access row zero, column zero in this bank, it sends the
row address.
And as the DM chip activates row address 0, the DM chip activates row address 0.
Takes some time and activation consists of bringing the data into the row buffer, sensing it, and
then now the data is ready to access.
So there's a timing parameter from when the memory controller says activate row address to the time
when it can say, oh, I want to read column X from that row.
And then after that time passes, the memory controller says I want to access column zero.
It sends the command to the DRAM chip, and the DRAM chip multiplexes out the right column and sends
it out to the memory controller.
So this is how the memory controller and the DRAM chip interact to get the data.
And this is how the DRAM chip operates at an abstract level.
We're going to see the lower level soon.
So this is interesting.
Now the data is actually inside this row buffer, right?
You activate a row and all of the row is in the row buffer, which means that you've actually cached
the row buffer.
This is actually one of the caches that we see.
First we're going to see more caching, but now row zero is there.
If the memory controller now wants row zero and column one some other column next to it, the next 8
bits, let's say, it doesn't need to activate the row again because the row is already in the sense
on fires open row is in the row buffer, the merit controller sense.
This is called the row buffer hit.
A cache hit memory controller needs to have a bookkeeping structure to understand which row is open
in which bank.
So there's a lot of bookkeeping that needs to be done.
You'll see this bookkeeping structure when we talk about cache's next lecture.
It's very similar structure in the end, and the memory control identifies based on a look up at that
bookkeeping structure, that row 0 is already open.
It says I'm not going to send the activate command because row 0 is already open, It's a row for a
hit.
So I'm just going to send a command to this DM bank saying I want column address 1, so give me
column one from the row that's open.
And the DM chip obliges because it cannot do anything by itself.
It basically obeys the command and delivers the data.
So that's the idea.
As you can see right now, if the memory controller again needs access to another column in the same
row, same thing happens.
It's a row buffer hit the memory controller sends.
There's only the column address with the column command.
Give me this column and the DAM ship obliges.
Now this sounds good, right?
We're not accessing the big array over there, we're accessing the small row buffer.
Much faster to do.
Now the problem happens if memory controller needs row one, for example some other row.
This takes some time.
Now the memory controller needs to send a command to the DAM bank saying I know you have row zero,
close it because I have a conflicting access.
So this is called a pre charge command in DM.
The DM chip bank closes the row, it takes some time and then the memory controller sends row address
1, the DM chip.
The DM bank activates row address 1.
The entire row gets sensed and placed in the row buffer and then the memory controller sends column
address 0 to get the right column out of the DM bank.
So we can see that different access have different timings right?
If the data that you're trying to access is already in the row buffer, the access is much faster
because it's cached.
Inside the DM chip.
There's a structure that's necessary for DM to operate because every row that the access needs to be
sensed and we will see why soon.
In the underlying structure, if the access that you have is to row that is not in the row buffer and
there's some other row in the row buffer that's called the row buffer conflicts.
The memory controller needs to 1st close the row, open another row and access the column it needs.
And this could actually take two to three X longer.
The disparity in these accesses like one of the a row hit maybe 25 nanoseconds, a row conflict maybe
75 nanoseconds.
This is, these are some potentially real numbers actually depending on the DM chip that you have.
So it really matters how you access data as you can see, right?
It's better if you actually program such that you keep accessing the same row or if the compiler
lays out the data such that you have maximise the locality in the row, meaning you access the row
as much as possible before needing some other row.
So you can see that this makes a huge difference potentially in the performance.
We're talking about not one nanosecond, we're talking about 25 versus 75 nanoseconds.
If you're A5 gigahertz processor multiply to get the clock cycles and you'll see 125 versus 5 times
of it 625, right.
OK, OK, I think I already said this, but that's under.
That's basically how a bank operates.
As I said, this is an abstraction.
Internally what happens is it's very difficult to build a bank that has 32,000 rows for various
reasons.
If you want to make the latency low, if you want to make the thing robust, especially with smaller
cells.
So internally what people do is divide the bank into smaller sub banks, Oregon subarrays, and each
subway is much smaller, maybe 512 or 1024 rows, and each of them has a local row buffer, local
sense amplifiers basically.
So internally things look like this and then you need to read the data out to a global row buffer
and then amplify it.
So internally things are more complicated as you can see.
And the main reason is it's too long latency to access a structure that's that big 32,000 rows
internally, subways also have smaller mats, but we're not going to talk about that right now.
So it actually works in the what I showed you is you break the Y dimension, but you also break the X
dimension in the end, X or Y, you can basically break both dimensions to smaller structures.
And that's your hierarchy.
OK, so this is another view of the DM bank from one of the papers that we have written.
And I'll, I'll recommend this for you, but I'm also going to build it up.
So internally, actually a subway consists of multiple mats in this particular case, like you have
two subways and two mats over here, but you can look at it on your own.
So let's go into a little bit more depth.
This is like it's, it's important for you to understand how things work and why things, why
decisions are made.
I think so this is a real DM module and a chip.
There is a lot of conflicting goals in memory design.
This is true for all memories in the end, especially stringent in DRAM because DRAM is actually has
a very interesting space.
This is the first memory that's outside the processor chip and it cannot be inside the processor
chip because the fabrication needs to be completely different as we will see because of the
capacitor and it's relatively fast.
It's not as slow as SSDs.
It's actually very fast compared to what we had in the before DRAM.
It's very high bandwidth, very relatively, again, very high capacity still, and it needs to be
designed really well.
And today actually, this is becoming much more important.
You may have heard that people are paying a lot more money for DM.
I think this is good because there's a reason for this, because memory is important, right?
So.
The cost is important, latency is important, bandwidth, parallelism, power, energy, reliable,
secure.
There are a lot of design decisions that you need to make.
Let's take a look at how things are designed.
So this is Adm chip with eight banks over here.
This is cartoon.
I'm showing you 2 subways in this eight banks.
This is what a sense amplifier looks like.
I'm going to build up the subway.
Actually, we're going to build up to this thing.
This is what a sense amplifier looked like.
And you have seen this before, right?
It's a 2.
It's a cross coupled inverter.
This is actually a strap, right?
There's a little bit more logic outside it to make it work, but I'm not going to talk about that.
But this is really the essence of a Sense am fire.
There's a top part, there's a bottom part.
There's an enable signal that we're going to add to the sense am fire because you need to enable it
to save power, etcetera.
There are two stable states of the Sense am fire.
This is how a logical 1 is sensed.
This is we're going to connect the bit line over here.
Bit line will come from the storage nodes.
So there's a VDD, meaning high voltage on the side and there's zero on the side.
When the sensor is enabled, you either have VDD on the side or 0 on the side.
And necessarily you should have the logical complement 0 and VDD on the other side, right?
So this is your logical one.
This is your logical 0.
Sounds good so far.
Right now the way this operates is you have some voltage level at the top, you have some voltage
level at the bottom.
When you disable the sense amplifier, nothing happens when you enable the sense amplifier.
What the sense amplifier does with some outside circuitry help also is it's basically senses that Vt
is.
If the Vt is greater than VB, it amplifies Vt to VDD and bottom voltage to 0.
Basically, that's the essence of sense amplification.
If voltage, if one of the voltages is greater than the other, the greater voltage is amplified to
the top level voltage VDD, the lower voltage is amplified down to 0.
That's what sense amplification means.
Basically, you sense either end of the, you sense the voltage in either end, and then you amplify
it.
OK, OK, now let's take a look at the DM cell.
We're going to connect the DM cell to the sense amplifiers.
This is the capacitor, right?
That's the DM cell.
We're not, we don't have the access transistor because that's not where data is stored.
Data is stored inside the capacitor and that's it.
Access transistor is there to access the data.
So empty state looks like this capacitor doesn't have any charge.
It's ideal empty state, of course, logical 0.
And this is the logical one, which is fully charged state.
Again, ideal.
Sometimes you lose charge, so it may not be ideal, but you may still be in the logical one state
because you're beyond the noise margins of the sense amplifier detection, right?
OK.
But this is the, let's say, beautiful world where things are logically 0 and black and white.
So the issue with the capacitor is it's very small, and we want it to be small.
I'm going to show you a real picture of it sometime later.
We want it to be small so that we can get higher capacity, right?
And because it's small, it cannot drive very large circuits.
So the data needs to be amplified over here.
And there's another issue, which is when you read the charge out, you destroy the state.
You mean you deplete the charge out of the capacitor.
So we actually connect the capacitor to the sensor fire so that we can solve those problems.
So this is the zero state in the capacitor.
It's the one state.
And we would like to sense this as zero, as you can see over here.
And we would like to sense this as one.
And the way we do it is by using an access transistor and a bit line.
So we have the DM cell, we have the access transistor, which is controlled by the word line, which
is not shown here.
And we have the bit line.
There's only one cell.
If you have more word lines that are going to be connected over here soon when you enable the access
transfer, what happens is OK.
I should also say that initially in what's called pre chart state and DRAM, it's ready to be sensed
state.
In other words, this bit line or the top part of the sensor amp fire set to reference voltage called
half VDD and the bottom part is also half VDD.
OK.
Ideally, you should not get any data out of that.
Now when you connect the capacitor to the bit line, capacitor charges are very little.
It perturbs the bit line, so it shares a little bit of charge over here.
So the voltage here increases and at some point the DM chip internally as a mechanism to enable the
sensor fire.
And when it enables the sensor fire, the sensor fire detects that difference and amplifies.
Advise the this bit line to VDD and the bottom part to 0.
That's how you actually detect this.
There's clearly a lot of circuit level, device level mechanism, but that's the essence of it, right?
It makes sense electrically.
OK, another thing that happens as the sense amplifier amplifies this to VDD, the charge on the bit
line gets driven into the capacitor.
Now the charge direction gets reversed and the capacitor becomes fully charged, which is what we
want because that's what we read from the capacitor, right?
So that's called the restoration of the charge.
So we sensed the charge, amplified it and restored it, right?
So that's those are the steps that happen when you read Adm cell, OK, now that's one DM cell and
that's one sense amplifier.
We don't want the Samsung fire for every DM cell because that's bad, right?
Why?
Because Sense amplifier is expensive, it has a lot of circuitry over there, at least 4 transistors
plus a bunch of other circuitry that is not shown.
We actually want to amortise the cost of that sensor fire across many DM cells.
That's why we actually put a lot of other DM cells across the bit line, right one on this side, on
the on the other side and this is now your bit line.
And we also want 2 dimensional of these things so that we can actually get more capacity.
And we extend the number of cells that are connected to the same word line.
So there is an array of sensamp files called the row buffer and there or row of sensamp files called
the row buffer that is used to sense any row that you enable by enabling a word line by providing
the address of the word line.
Right, That's the idea.
So you can see that the magic is gone.
This is how DM all DM all memory, all main memory works and there needs to be an enable signal for
that.
And then there needs to be a decoder that decodes the word line address clearly.
And there needs to be a multiplexer that takes out the appropriate part of the row as we have seen
earlier.
OK, and that's the salary.
So this is essentially 1 sub race.
This is called a sub race.
And then there could be multiple sub race.
As you can see this is a chip where you have two sub race per DM back.
In modern chips, you have hundreds to thousands of subways in Adam Bank, and there needs to be some
bank IO so that when you actually read the data from one row into the array of sands amp fires, you
get all 8 kilobits.
And when you want to get one column, like 8 bits or 64 bits out, whatever the granularity is, that
data gets transferred to something, some other sense.
I'm fire over here.
It's called a global sense.
I'm fire or global IO logic.
There could be multiple steps over there also.
But essentially there needs to be a smaller granularity access mechanism.
And it's good to think about this because you need interconnects over here, right?
You supply the address, one row gets enabled, and that enable draw goes over here into the array of
sensamp fires for that particular subway.
And then you need to supply the column address.
They need to go through much longer interconnects, right?
And those interconnects are not only long, but they're also much wider because you need to support
the travel of data across a much larger distance.
And to do that robustly, you need a lot more voltage and a lot more width of these interconnects.
So they cannot be 8 kilobytes, they can be only 64 bits, for example.
OK, so basically this is our DM chip.
You have a memory channel of eight bits.
You have a shared internal bus across different banks.
Each bank gets access to the bus depending on which one is transferring data.
And we've seen the operation, but I'll also discuss it so that we can complete it.
If you want to access, let's say this element over here, in this row, you first activate the row.
You supply the row address, so that row gets activated.
This is the element that you want and then the memory controller sends a read write supplying the
column address and that element gets read out OK.
So there needs to be interconnects to support this and then eventually the memory controller sends a
pre charge command which clears the row from the row buffer so that you can bring another row over
there.
Makes sense hopefully right?
OK, so this is essentially how DM operates.
There's of course more detail, but we don't need to go into it.
If you want more, you can take a look at this paper that we wrote with one of my prior PhD students.
Let's take a look at the top down view.
Also.
Wait, bottom up view?
Bottom up view, Sorry, No, no, no, we, we already went through all of those views.
Sorry.
Let's take a look at how things get transferred from the DM chip to the processor.
So.
If you in in the end you need to map the data appropriately.
For example, if your access granularity is a cache block granularity 64 bytes let's say, which is
the granularity in many CPU based systems today and also GPU based system.
It could be larger in GPUs.
You need to have a mapping of that physical 64 bytes to the underlying hierarchy.
Right here you can see that the 64 bytes is mapped to channel 0, rank zero, dem zero.
And the hope is that you're going to get all of those 64 bytes quickly out of that.
You don't need to switch channels, you don't need to switch banks, etcetera, right?
Not switch banks.
You don't need to switch ranks.
OK, internally, this is what the mapping looks like.
This is our rank 0.
Internally, you have 8 chips and you get 64 bits at a time.
We want a 64 byte cache blocked or, right?
So you're going to bring it 64 bits at a time over 8 clock cycles in the event.
So one access will give us 64 bits.
So this is row zero, column zero, for example.
It's going to give us 8 bits from each chip and 64 bits from all of the chips.
That gives us the 1st 8 bytes in the cache block, and then we're going to go to row zero, column
one.
That will give us the next 8 bytes, and then we're going to go to row zero, column two.
We're going to get next 8 bytes and you get the idea.
So it takes 8 IO cycles to transfer the entire 64 byte cache block.
And during the process, 8 comms are read sequentially.
The good news is this is all except for the first access.
It's all coming from the row buffer, right?
Because it's sequential access.
And if you map your data nicely, which is what you should do all the time, which is what systems do,
I should say you don't need to deal with this at the level of the programming today.
But essentially it's all coming out of the row buffer.
Any questions?
OK, hopefully this is fascinating and interesting, right?
So we have some time.
I'll introduce some of the memory technologies and this will hopefully be a good stepping stone for
the next time.
So we talk about DRAM.
This is dynamic capacitor charged stores the value and you have one capacitor, it's very cheap
basically as you can see, right?
And you have one access transistor and we already said that this cell loses charge over time, so it
needs to be refreshed.
That is not going to exist in SRAM.
So we're going to talk about memory technology a little bit.
I should also say that this is the virtual view of the DRAM.
This is what a physical view looks like.
And under scanning electron microscope capacitors are actually etched like this in the DRAM.
You can see that they're huge.
They're in the three-dimensional and it's actually fascinating.
Manufacturing these chips is not easy.
As you can see, the bit line looks like this.
The word line is over here, but you can see that the capacitors are very dense and close to each
other.
And this is one of the reasons why things are quite noisy when you actually read OK, static random
access memory.
You've also seen this.
This is 2 cross coupled inverters.
They store a single bit and there's a feedback path that enables the store value to stay in the cell
as long as it's powered on.
That's good.
You have 4 transistors for storage.
It's immediately much more expensive as you can see, but that's not enough.
You cannot access this thing.
And you know that from very early on.
We need 2 transistors for access.
And usually you need 2 transistors to enable differential sensing in the in SRAM, which we're not
going to get into.
But in some technologies, especially when you have very low voltage, you may need more than two
transistors also.
So at least six transistors, as you can see, expensive.
So memory bank is organised similarly regardless of whether or not you have SRAM or DRAM, right?
Essentially you have some 2 dimensional storage array, you have a row decoder, you have a column
decoder, you have an address register.
Most significant bits of the address provide the essentially the row address, least significant bits
of the address provide the column address.
And then you read data out in SRAM you supply, you can supply the entire address because it's on
chip.
Usually that's the assumption for off chip memories because you don't want to have very large
address buses because these are actually driving interconnects outside the chip.
You supply the row address first and then you supply the column address.
That enables things to have less, fewer pins.
So off chip and on chip you have different trade-offs.
We've actually seen a lot of this.
This is actually happening for both SRAM and DM.
So this is a good place to stop.
Now that you're familiar with memory technology, organization, how things work, we're going to build
up to a memory hierarchy and we'll talk about caches next week.
And I think we have only one lecture next week, Right?
OK, another Singleton.
OK, have a good weekend.
I'll see you next week.